<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The scattered sheep sought after 1. In a lamentation over the general losse of the powerful presence of God in his people, since the dayes of the apostles, with a particular bewailing of the withering and death of those precious buddings forth of life, which appeared in many at the beginning of the late troubles in these nations, with the proper way of recovery for such, 2. In some propositions concerning the only way of salvation, where is an answer given to that great objection, that the light which convinceth of sin, is the light of a natural conscience, and a brief account rendred of the ground of mens misunderstanding Scriptures, 3. In exposing to view the fundamental principle of the Gospel, upon which the redeemed spirit is built, 4. And in some questions and answers, by way of catechism, for the sake of the simple hearted, directing to that principle, and fixing in it / by Isaac Penington.</title>
            <author>Penington, Isaac, 1616-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 81 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1188</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18193</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13044858</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13044858</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96894</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96894)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 748:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The scattered sheep sought after 1. In a lamentation over the general losse of the powerful presence of God in his people, since the dayes of the apostles, with a particular bewailing of the withering and death of those precious buddings forth of life, which appeared in many at the beginning of the late troubles in these nations, with the proper way of recovery for such, 2. In some propositions concerning the only way of salvation, where is an answer given to that great objection, that the light which convinceth of sin, is the light of a natural conscience, and a brief account rendred of the ground of mens misunderstanding Scriptures, 3. In exposing to view the fundamental principle of the Gospel, upon which the redeemed spirit is built, 4. And in some questions and answers, by way of catechism, for the sake of the simple hearted, directing to that principle, and fixing in it / by Isaac Penington.</title>
                  <author>Penington, Isaac, 1616-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96894:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96894:1"/>
            <p>THE Scattered ſheep Sought after.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In a Lamentation over the general loſſe of the powerful preſence of God in his people, ſince the dayes of the Apoſtles, with a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular bewailing of the withering and death of thoſe precious bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings forth of life, which appeared in many at the beginning of the late troubles in theſe Nations, with the proper way of recovery for ſuch.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In ſome Propoſitions concerning the only way of ſalvation; where is an anſwer given to that great objection, That the light which convinceth of ſin, is the light of a natural conſcience; and a brief account rendred of the ground of mens miſunderſtanding Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In expoſing to view the fundamental Principle of the Goſpel, upon which the redeemed Spirit is built.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And in ſome Queſtions and Anſwers, (by way of Catechiſm, for the ſake of the ſimple hearted) directing to that Principle, and fixing in it.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Iſaac Pennington.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>When <hi>Ephraim</hi> ſpoke trembling, he exalted himſelf in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> but when he offended in <hi>Baal,</hi> he died. And now they ſin more and more, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>Therefore they ſhall be as the morning cloud, and as the early dew, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hoſ. 13.1, 2, 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Yea his ſpring ſhall become drie, and his fountain ſhall be dried up, <bibl>
                  <hi>ver. 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>We have all been as ſheep going aſtray; but bleſſed be the everlaſting Arm, which hath gathered any of us to the Shepherd and Biſhop of our ſouls.</q>
            <q>O come to the fold, O ſcattered Sheep come to the fold: Wander no longer from mountain to hill, but remember your reſting place, the ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> reſting place of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> even the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>untain of the Lords houſe, where <hi>Iſrae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> may lie d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wn and feed in peace, and no ravenous beaſt can diſturb.</q>
            <q>O houſe of <hi>Jacob</hi> let whoredome, wine, and new wine, no longer ſtea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> away your hearts, but come let us walk in the light of the Lord.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year 1665.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:96894:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96894:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The PREFACE,</head>
            <p>MY people have committed two evils: they have forſaken me the Fountain of living waters, and hewed them out Ciſterns, broken Ciſterns that can hold no water. This was ever and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non the complaint of the Lord concerning Iſrael, from the beginning to the end. The Lord did delight to beget, nouriſh, and bring up that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple for himſelf; but they were almoſt continually revolting from him, and rebelling againſt him. He did mighty things for them, but they ſtill forgot him. He redeemed them by his outſtretched Arm, he fed them, he defended them, but they knew him not <hi>(Iſa. 1.3.)</hi> but decked themſelves with the ornaments which they had from him, and then lift up the heel againſt him, <hi>Ezek. 16.7. &amp;c. Deut. 32.15.</hi> In plain terms, they got what knowledge they could from him into their own veſſels, and then they could ſet up for themſelves, live of themſelves, without freſh bublings up of life from the ſpring, from whence their knowledg came (the Prieſts ſaid not, Where is the Lord? but could handle the Law, and teach the knowledge of it without him: and the Prophets could propheſie by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Spirit, <hi>Jer. 2.8.</hi>) And thus the Lord God of life lived not in them, but they lived upon ſuch things as once came from the life, but (being ſeparated from the ſpring) were dead, and nouriſhed but the dead part in them, the part eſtranged from God. And thus, though their profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions were great, and they multiplied prayers, and ſacrifices, and faſts, and drew nigh to God with their lips, yet their hearts were far from him. They had forſaken the Fountain, they drank not of the waters of the ſpring (of the rock that followed them) but they drank of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of their own Ciſterns. They ſet up that knowledge of the Law for their light, which they had hewed out with the tools of their own under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, without that ſpirit that wrote it. This was <hi>Iſraels</hi> error of old; they drank very zealouſly of the waters of the Law, but they drank it not from he ſpring, but out of the Ciſterns which themſelves had hewed.</p>
            <p>And as it was thus with <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old ſo hath it been with <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſince. The Chriſtian <hi>Iſrael</hi> hath been alwaies back-ſliding, alwaies forgetting the Lord; ſtill getting what they could from him to live of themſelves, but refuſing to live on h m: getting what knowledge they could from the Scriptures without him, getting what they could from their exerciſes and experiences, but neglecting the ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of their life. And ſo this <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:96894:3"/>
alſo dies, this <hi>Iſrael</hi> likewiſe withers, and becomes a ſcorn to the beathen: for though they ſpeak great words of their God, yet they themſelves are but as the heathen, uncircumciſed like them, unacquainted with the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue &amp; power of life like them, alwaies ſtriving againſt ſin in that which cannot conquer, and ſo they alſo are ſlaves under their luſts and corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, like the heathen, and know not the truth which makes free indeed.</p>
            <p>Exceeding great hath been the apoſtacy of this age. Mighty was the appearance of God inwardly in his peoples Spirits, mighty was the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of God outwardly in the Nation, many waies and great hopes there was of a thorow reformation. But how ſuddenly was the pure Spirit of the Lord forgotten, and departed from, and his work overturned both within and without; inwardly in his peoples ſpirits, and outwardly in the Nation, whoſe revolting was but a type of the inward. And how hath the Spirit of the Lord mourned after his people, often reproving them for their back-ſlidings! but they have been (as <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, like the deaf Adder) juſtifying themſelves, and complaining againſt the witneſſes of God (as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did againſt his Prophets) who from the Lord teſtifie againſt them. And it cannot be otherwiſe; for the dead waters in <hi>Iſraels</hi> hewen Ciſterns, will never agree with the waters of the living Fountain, but will withstand their testimony.</p>
            <p>How ſhall the charmer charm wiſely enough, to make apoſtate <hi>Iſrael</hi> hearken to his voice! I have not back ſlidden, ſaith one in one form; I have not back-ſlidden, ſaith another in another form: <hi>I</hi> am not back-ſlidden ſaith one in one notion; <hi>I</hi> am not back ſlidden ſaith another, in another notion; I am believing, hoping, and waiting in what the Lord hath already revealed, and following on to know him. This hath been thy manner from thy youth, that thou obedſt not my word, but ſtill haſt been justifying thy ſelf, as if thou hadſt obeyed. And yet your back-ſlidings are written upon your foreheads, as with the point of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, for who among you retains his freſhneſſe? an evident demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ye are departed from the ſpring, and hold your knowledge, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riences, and h pes in the dead part, and your chiefeſt prop of comfort is the remembrance of what ye once had. Ah poor, barren, dead ſouls, is this your beſt ſupport? Return, return, enter into the houſe of mourning, and let the living lay it to heart.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96894:3"/>
            <head>A Lamentation with a call to mourning and Lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the royal ſeed, the plant of renown, the living off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of eternity; O daughter of <hi>Sion,</hi> who didſt once ſhine with the beauty and glory of life, what is become of thee! how art thou held captive, and chained up in <hi>Babylon!</hi> how doſt thou lie fullied among the pots! how are the wings of thy Dove clipped! how art thou covered, and polluted with the filth of the whole earth!</p>
            <p>O take up a Lamentation, weep O <hi>Iſrael,</hi> mourn O daughter of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> bewail thy widdow-hood, thy deſolation, thy loſs of Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, thy ſad captivity, thy baniſhment out of thine own land, and thy thraldom in the land of thine enemy.</p>
            <p>What is become of thy God, the mighty God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> whoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtretched arme hath been able to ſave and redeem his ſeed out of bondage? What enemy hath been able to ſtand before him? What wild Boar out of the Wood, or wild Beaſt out of the Forreſt, was able to break into his Vineyard, while he kept the fence? where is that arm that ſmote <hi>Rahab,</hi> and ſlew the <hi>Dragon?</hi> Where is that hook that he was wont to put into the noſtrils of the <hi>Leviathan? Pharaoh</hi> is alive, the wiſe <hi>Egyptians</hi> have power, <hi>Egypt</hi> holds the ſeed in bondage, <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bal, Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Amalek,</hi> the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> with the inhabitants of <hi>Tire,</hi> are all able to ſmite <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to ſtop up the well-ſprings of life. Awake O arm of the Lord, and awaken <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that thou again maiſt become his Saviour in the ſight of all the Nations; and let all the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> being awakened, mourn in the Spirit of the Lord after the Lord.</p>
            <p>What is become of thy <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> the Lords anointed, the Captain of the Lords hoaſts, the Angel of the Covenant of life, who was wont to go in and out before thee in fighting of the Lords battels, who was the Prince and Saviour in the land of peace and reſt, who walked in the midſt of the candleſticks, who was thy King thy ſhepherd thy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wherein thou worſhippedſt, and the eternal light of thy life in the Land of the living?</p>
            <p>What is become of that holy ſpirit which q ickned thee to God,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:96894:4"/>
and which lived in thee being quickned? which kept thee alive in him that liveth, and made thee taſte the ſweetneſſe of life continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally? Where is the anointing, which ſuppled thee all over with the oyl of gladneſſe and ſalvation? Where is the comforter, that refreſhed thy ſpirit continually, and led thee into all truth, teaching thee all the things of God, according to thy meaſure of growth in the life? Where is the Spirit of thy Father, which Spirited thee with thy Fathers nature, which begot and brought forth the life, power, glory, majeſty, eternity of thy Father in thee?</p>
            <p>What is become of <hi>Sion,</hi> the holy Mount, whereon thou waſt built? <hi>Sion,</hi> the fortreſſe of holineſſe, where is it? What is become of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> the holy City, thy Mother whereof thou waſt born? What is become of that Covenant of life, in whoſe womb thou waſt begotten and brought forth, and by whoſe milk, and breath thou waſt afterward nouriſhed and brought up?</p>
            <p>Where are all the fruits of the holy Land? the pleaſant Grapes, the ſweet Figs, the precious Olives, that yeelded Wine and Oyl to make the heart glad, and to refreſh the countenance of the Lord of Life? Where's the joy in the Lord, the obedience to the Lord, the praying, the praiſing, the living, the walking in his Spirit, the entering into and bringing forth fruit in his pure underſtanding, and in his holy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted will and movings in the purified heart?</p>
            <p>Alas, alas, <hi>Babylon</hi> hath prevailed, her King hath reigned, <hi>Sion</hi> hath been held in bonds, and that which hath ſprung up under her name, hath been the filthy off ſpring of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the ſeed of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Harlots; and theſe have brought forth ſower fruit, loathſome fruit, finely painted to the view of that eye which cannot ſearch into it, but loathſom in its nature. This hath been the State of the apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy ſince the daies of the Apoſtles, wherein that which hath not been of God hath reigned, and that which hath been of God hath ſuffered, and been reproached as if it had not been of God, and hath panted and mourned after the ſpringing up of the ſpring of its life, and its gathering into it.</p>
            <p>The deep ſenſe of this hath afflicted my Soul from my tender years, the eternal witneſſe awakening in me, and the eternal light manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the darkneſſe all along unto me, though I knew not that it was the light, but went about to meaſure its appearances in me, by words which it ſelf had formerly ſpoken to others, and ſo ſet up my own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and comprehenſion as the meaſurer, although I did not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:96894:4"/>
then perceive or think that I did ſo. Thus continually (through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) I ſlew the life, and ſold my ſelf for a thing of nothing, even for ſuch an appearance of life, as my underſtanding part could judge moſt agreeable to Scriptures. This the Lord blew upon, though its comlineſſe was unutterable (the life ſtill feeding my Spirit under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, from whence ſprang an inward beauty and freſhneſſe:) then ſuch a day (or rather night) of darkneſſe and diſtreſſe overtook me, as would make the hardeſt heart melt to hear the relation of; yet the Lord was in that darkneſſe, and he preſerved me, and was forming of me to himſelf; and the taſte I had then of him, was far beyond what ever I had known in the pureſt ſtrains of my Religion formerly. And the Lord powerfully ſhut up my underſtanding, and preſerved my life from the betrayer. But yet that was not perfectly deſtroyed in me, upon which the Tempter might work: and the Lord ſuffered him to lay a ſnare, and my feet were intangled unawares, in ſo much as the ſimplicity was betrayed, and the fleſhly part grew wiſe by thoſe exerciſes wherewith the Lord had tried me. This poyſoned me, this hurt me, this ſtruck at the root of my life, and death inſenſibly grew upon me. The Devil (the envious ſeeds-man) couſened me with the Image, which before I had had in the truth opening my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing part (by the ſubtilty of temptation and deceit) which the Lord had been deſtroying; and letting that in, which the Lord had ſhut out: and then the Lord took away, and ſhut up from that part, that which before he had opened to the ſeed, whereby the way of life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſtopped, and the way of death opened in a Myſtery. And then I could talk of univerſal love, of ſpiritual liberty, &amp;c. and wait for the glorious appearance of life, having loſt that which formerly gave me the ſenſe of its nature: yea, at length I could ſeek to the creatures for what they could yeeld, and ſtrive to rub out the time of my miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry without the immediate preſence of the life of the Creator. And as for this deſpicable people (whom I now own in the Lord) I could meaſure them, I could fathome them: I could own their ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and yet ſee their ſhortneſſe, and could (with ſatisfaction to my ſpirit) write death upon them, as the end of that diſpenſation of life, into which I ſaw them entering, and in part entred. Here was my ſtanding, when the Lord drew his ſword upon me, and ſmote me in the very inmoſt of my ſoul: by which ſtroke (lying ſtill a while un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it) my eyes came to be opened; and then I ſaw the blindneſſe of that eye, which was able to ſee ſo far, and the narrowneſſe of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:96894:5"/>
that heart and ſpirit, which was ſo large and vaſt in comprehending: and my Soul bowed down to the Lord to ſlay this, to ſtarve this, to make a fool of this; yea my deſire was (to preſent ſence) as great after the death of this, as after the enjoyment of life in the Lord.</p>
            <p>And now this hath opened a freſh ſpring of ſorrow in me, a mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the juſt one, which hath been ſlain by me. O how cruelly, how often have I murthered that, which came to give me life! how often have I ſought to have my own underſtanding, my own compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, my own will and affections in Religion live, and the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pure immortal principle die! though I did not then call it my own (as other men do not now) but took it to be of God, and to be the thing that was to live: for I alſo was deceived, and thought the Baſtard (which was a falſe conception) was to inherit not knowing him to be the Baſtard, but taking him for the right heir. And my ſoul is exceedingly enlarged in me towards thoſe, who at this day lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the power of the ſame deceit, who have ſlain the Lord of life as well as I, and in whom the contrary nature lives under a covering; who cannot poſſibly ſee that this (which now lives in them) is not the heir until the ſame eye be opened in them.</p>
            <p>The life that was ſtirring, at the beginning of the trouble of theſe Nations, was very precious: it did unite to God, it did unite to one another; it kindled an univerſal ſence of the captivity, of the bondage, of the great oppreſſion of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and a joynt cry went up to God for deliverance. And God heard the cry, and aroſe to deliver, and did begin to break the yoke, both outwardly in the Nation, and inwardly in peoples ſpirits.</p>
            <p>But then the tempter did alſo ſet himſelf at work, again to intangle <hi>Iſrael.</hi> For this end he brings forth likeneſſes of that which <hi>Iſrael</hi> deſired, and was ſeeking after. He brings forth ſeveral forms of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to allure ſome with, ſeveral ſorts of notions to allure others with, ſeveral freſh appearances of life, of love, of liberty, to tempt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God aſide from following that ſpirit which roſe up to deliver. Thus comes he forth, and prevails: he divides in <hi>Jacob,</hi> and ſcatters in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> drawing one part to this form, another part towards that form; one to this Notion, another to that Notion; one to this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Image, another to that ſpiritual Idol; and all from the life, all from the power, all from the Saviour, all from the deliverer: and ſo the work ſtops. It ſtops in the Nation, and it ſtops in peoples ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and men generally wheele about, and center again, and apply
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:96894:5"/>
themſelves to make Images like the Images they had deſtroyed: and ſo the Captivity returns, <hi>Iſrael</hi> is turned back into his bonds, and the Spirit which oppreſſed him before, again cruſheth him, and rules over him. And ſo great hath the breach been upon <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the world is become hardened, and thinks there's an end of this work of God, and now they may venture again to ſettle both Church and State, upon the old Principles of that wiſdom which the Lord was ſhaking.</p>
            <p>And now, where is the people whom the Lord was redeeming; where is the praying people, the panting people, the mourning peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the people that could have travelled from ſea to ſea to have had the will of God revealed? are they not run into the earth? is not the ſpirit of the earth come over them? are they not dividing the ſpoils? The inward Jew, the renewed nature is ſunk, loſt, made a prey of, the Gentile, the Heatheniſh Spirit hath riſen up, and ſeated it ſelf in a form of worſhip, or in ſome high Notions of knowledge, on which that Spirit (which knows not the Tree of life) loves to feed. Some are ſtark dead, no ſence at all in them, but life quite ſwallowed up of death. Others perhaps are ſtill preſſing towards the Kingdom, but in the wrong nature, in that which ſhall never obtain; and they may there meet with ſome enjoyments, but not enjoyments from or of the true thing, but of the likeneſſe which the enemy hath painted to deceive them with: and they may alſo wait and hope that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom will come, and yet be out of that which knows its coming, and can alone prepare the heart for its appearance. Yea ſome are got ſo high, that they are even in the Throne: They have the love, the life, the liberty, the joy, the peace of the Kingdom (as they imagine.) They can reign as Kings without us, without that nature and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wherein our life lies. But theſe mighty ones, theſe Princes the Lord will pull from their ſeat, and raiſe up the humble, the meek, the low in heart, the beggar from the dunghil, and give to him the Throne of his glory.</p>
            <p>Now this, my life in love ſaith to you all, as the proper and only way of your recovery and redemption, come to that which can judge you. <hi>Sion is to be redeemed with judgement, and her converts with righteouſneſſe.</hi> If <hi>Sion</hi> be redeemed, if the ſeed be again raiſed, that Spirit which hath got up above it (and keepeth it down) muſt be judged, and brought under by judgement. How was <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old to be recovered from her idolatries and whoredoms, but by
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:96894:6"/>
owning and coming to that light in the Prophets which manifeſted, and judged it? Ye alſo have worſhiped Idols, ye alſo have run a whoring from the Lord, and have been inflamed with Idols under every green Tree. Every new Idol, every freſh appearance, every lively likeneſs hath tempted you aſide from the living God. When one way of worſhip hath been dry and barren, ye have left that; when ſome notions of things have appeared empty and ſhallow, ye have been weary of them; but the next new Idol, under the next green Tree, hath drawn you aſide into the bed of whoredom, where ye have loſt true fellowſhip with the true God of life, and have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed of the ſeed of life, which he began to quicken and raiſe from the dead. Now come to that which judgeth the Idol, the Idol-maker, the whoriſh Spirit which tempteth aſide from the true husband, and that Spirit which is liable to be Tempted; and let theſe be cut down by the judgment, and then the true ſeed of life will ſpring and flouriſh again. There is no other way, be not deceived. That muſt be awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in you which can judge you, and muſt bring forth its judgment in you unto Victory, if life in you ever riſe and get the dominion over death. And that Spirit which now rules in you (and keeps the life down) knows this very well, and therefore endeavours all it can, to keep you from owning judgement. He would faine keep the light in others from judging you, <hi>Do not judge,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>All judgement is committed to the Son.</hi> True, but ſhall not the light of the Son judge? ſhall not the light of that candle which the Lord hath lighted in one heart, diſcover and judg the darkneſs in another heart? Light doth make manifeſt, and its manifeſtation is its judgement, the uttering of the words are but the declaration of what the light in the heart hath done before, and cannot but do; for as long as it is light, where ever it come, it will and cannot but diſcover and judge the darkneſs it meets with, though the darkneſs cannot owne either its diſcovery or its judgment, but muſt needs except againſt it. Now if he cannot do this (which is utterly impoſſibly for the dark ſpirit to do) then, in the next place, he fortifies and hardens the heart, as much as he can, from receiving the judgement, by perſwading him to look upon it as the judgement of another ſpirit like his own, and not as the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the light, And ſo what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid concerning mans judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (that it was a ſmall matter to him to be judged by mans judgement) the ſame will he ſay concerning this judgement.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:96894:6"/>
And yet, as the greateſt judgement of man, in the higheſt ſtrain of the comprehending part, ſhall fall: ſo the loweſt judgement of the light in the weakeſt child ſhall ſtand; and all the exalted ones of the earth ſhall in due time fall before it, though now (in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent elevation of their minds) they may riſe high above it, and trample it down. Therefore be not afraid to judge deceit. O ye weak ones, but be ſure that the light alone in you judge; and lie very low in the light, that that part, which the light in you judgeth in others, get not up in you, while the light is making uſe of you to judge it in others.</p>
            <p>And now ye poor loſt ſouls (who find the need of judgment, and any willingneſs within you to embrace it) wait firſt, for the riſing of the Judge of Iſrael in your hearts, and in the next place wait for the joyning of your hearts to him; both which are to be done by his eternal light, which manifeſts and gives his life. In the loweſt ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this light there is the judgement, and there is the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (who is not ſevered from the leaſt degree or merſure of his own light) bow down to him, kiſs his feet; know the nature of the thing, and ſubject to it: worſhip him here in his humiliation, receive him in his ſtrokes, in his ſmitings (and obſerve, and turn from that in your ſelves which ſmites him) and ye ſhall one day ſee him in his majeſty, in the power of his love, in his everlaſting healings and embraces. And know aſſuredly, that that which will not worſhip him here, will not be fit to worſhip him there, nor ſhall not; but ſhall only tremble at the dread of his majeſty, and be confounded at the ſweetneſs of his love, but not be able to bow down to it in the true life. For that Spirit which is out of the life, is ſhut out in its higheſt deſires, hopes, attainments, enjoyments, ſeemingly ſpiritual reſt, univerſal love, liberty and peace, as well as in its darkeſt and groſſeſt paths of pollution. Therefore wait to know the nature of things, that ye may not be deceived with the higheſt, choiceſt, and moſt powerful appearances of death in the exacteſt image of life, not ſtumble at true life in its loweſt and weakeſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance. And this ye can only attain to by a birth of, and growth up in the true wiſdome, which ſlaies that ſpirit which lives on the ſame things in the comprehenſion, and gathers a ſtock of knowledge and experiences in its own underſtanding
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:96894:7"/>
part. Theſe are words of tender love, and they will alſo be words of true life, where the Fathers earth opens to drink them in, to whoſe good pleaſure and bleſſing my ſoul commends them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Some Propoſitions concerning the only way of Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That there is no way of being ſaved from ſin and wrath eternal, but by that Chriſt alone which died at Jeruſalem.</hi> There is no name, vertue, life, or power under heaven given, by which loſt man may be ſaved, but his alone.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That there is no way of being ſaved by him, but through receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him into the heart by a living faith, and having him formed in the heart.</hi> Chriſt ſaves not as he ſtands without at the door knock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but as he is let in; and being let in, he brings in with him that life, power, and mercy which breaks down the wall of partition, unites to God, and ſaves. The Jews could not be ſaved formerly by belief of a Meſſiah to come (with the obſervation of all the Laws and Ordinances of <hi>Moſes</hi>) nor can any now be ſaved by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of a Chriſt already come (with obſervation of all that the Apoſtles Commanded or Practiſed) but alone by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of him into the heart, who there works out the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That there is no way of receiving Chriſt into the heart, and of having him formed there, but by receiving the light of his ſpirit, in which light he is, and dwels:</hi> Keep out the light of the ſpirit, keep out Chriſt; let in the light of the ſpirit, let in Chriſt: for the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Son are light, and are alone known and received in the light, but never out of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That the way of receiving the light of the ſpirit into the heart</hi> (and thereby uniting with the Father and the Son) <hi>is by hearkning to, and receiving its convictions of ſin there.</hi> The firſt operation of the ſpirit towards man lying in the ſin, is to convince him of the ſin: and he that receives not the convincing light of the ſpirit, the work is ſtopped in him at the very firſt; and Chriſt can never come to be formed in him, becauſe that light, whereby he ſhould be formed, is kept out. And then he may talk of Chriſt, and practiſe duties (pray, read, and meditate much) and gather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts from promiſes, and run into Ordinances, and be exceeding zealous and affectionate in all theſe, and yet periſh in the end.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:96894:7"/>
Yea the Devil will let him alone (if not help him in all this) know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he hath him the ſurer thereby, he being (by the ſtrict obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of theſe) kept out of the danger of his condition, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, perhaps, he might be made ſenſible of.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But I may be deceived in hearkning to a light within, for while I think that I therein hearken to the light of the Spirit, it may prove but the light of a natural conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If it ſhould be but the light of a natural Conſcience, and it draw thee from ſin (which ſeparates from God) and ſo prepare thee for the underſtanding, believing, and receiving what the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſaith of Chriſt, this is no very bad deceit; but if in the reſult it ſhould prove to have been the light of the Spirit, and thou all thy life time haſt took it for the light of a natural conſcience (and ſo haſt deſpiſed, or at leaſt neglected, if not reproached it) thou wilt then find that this was a very bad deceit.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I can ſhew thee by expreſs Scripture, that it is the work of the ſpirit to convince of ſin, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.8. And again, that the Law (which is ſpiritual) manifeſteth that which is corrupt and carnal, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14. But where canſt thou ſhew me from Scripture, that a natural conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence can convince of ſin?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Let any man give heed to the light in his heart, he ſhall find it to diſcover his moſt inward, his moſt ſecret, his moſt ſpiritual evils, which a natural light cannot do: for that which is natural cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover that which is ſpiritual.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Apoſtle ſaith, That it is the grace which hath appeared to all men, which teacheth not only godlineſſe, but alſo ſobriety and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11 12. The light of the falne nature is darkneſſe, can teach nothing of God; what any man learns now of the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of God, he learns by grace, which ſhines in the darkneſſe of mans nature, to leaven it with the true knowledg, though man (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing darkneſſe) can by no means comprehend it, and ſo cannot give it its true name.</p>
            <p>Therefore take heed leſt (through ignorance) ye blaſpheme the holy light of the pure Spirit, calling that natural (looking on it with the carnal eye) which with the ſpiritual eye is ſeen to be ſpiritual. For thou that doſt this, wilt be be alſo erring on the other hand, calling thy carnal meanings and conceivings (about the mind of the Spirit of God in Scripture) ſpiritual. And he that thus puts darkneſſe for light, muſt needs put light for darkneſſe;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:96894:8"/>
and then call evil good, and good evil: and ſo err from the Spirit of God in the whole courſe of his Religion, even in the moſt inward exerciſes of it.</p>
            <p>Man by nature is dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes, quite dead, and his conſcience wholly dark. That which giveth him the ſenſe of his death, and of his darkneſſe, muſt be another thing then his nature, even the light of the ſpirit of Chriſt, ſhining in his dark heart and conſcience. It is the ſeed of the woman which not only deſtroyes, but alſo diſcovers all the deeds of the Serpent. Now this ſeed, this light is one in all, though there have been ſeveral diſpenſations of it: One to the Heathen, in whom it ſprings up after an hidden manner, even as it were naturally, from whence it had the name of the <hi>Light of Nature</hi> (though it be the miſtery of life and ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hid in them, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.27. <hi>this miſtery in the Gentiles,</hi> it is ill tranſlated <hi>among:</hi>) another to the Jews, in whom it was more vigorouſly ſtirred up by a Law given, who by types, and ſhadows, and righteous exerciſes according to the Law, were to be awakened to the living principle, <hi>Mich.</hi> 6.8. Another to the Chriſtians, in whom it was livelily brought forth to light and life, by an eſpecial diſpenſation of grace; in ſo much as that which was the <hi>Miſtery in the Gentiles,</hi> and vailed from the Jews, being opened in them, was found to be <hi>Chriſt the hope,</hi> Col. 1.27. But under all theſe diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, the generality of men have fallen ſhort of the glory of God, and miſſed of the ſubſtance. Therefore the Lord God is now bringing forth the ſubſtance it ſelf, but under ſuch a vail as hides it from the eye of mans wiſdome, under what diſpenſation ſoever he be, and how high ſoever in that diſpenſation. To ſome it ſeems natural, to others legal; to ſome it ſeems from the power of Satan (or at leaſt they pretend ſo) to others it ſeems the miniſtry of <hi>John Baptiſt.</hi> Thus men gueſs at it in the wiſdome of their comprehenſions, waiting the true line and plummet to meaſure it by.</p>
            <p>Now to you who have not waited to learn in the wiſdome of God the names of things (which there are given according to their nature) but in the forwardneſſe of your ſpirits, from your gathered knowledg, without the living power have ventured to call that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, which in the eternal wiſdome is ſeen to be ſpiritual (and which hath been able to effect that, which all that knowledge which ye call ſpiritual, could never do) let me propoſe th conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:96894:8"/>
of one Scripture to your Conſciences in the ſight of God.</p>
            <p>The Scripture is that in <hi>Job</hi> 28.12. to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where ſhall wiſdome be found? and where is the place of under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding? Man knoweth not the price thereof, neither is it found in the land of the living. The deep ſaith, it is not in me; and the ſea ſaith, not in me. It cannot be gotten for gold, neither ſhall ſilver be weighed for the price thoreof, &amp;c. Whence then cometh wiſdome, and where is the place of underſtanding? ſeeing it is hid from the eyes of all living, and kept cloſe from the fowls of Heaven. Deſtruction and death ſay, we have heard the fame thereof with our ears. God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth the way thereof, and he knoweth the place thereof, &amp;c. And he ſaid unto man, Behold, the fear of the Lord, that is wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to depart from evil is underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now conſider well:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Is this natural wiſdome or ſpiritual wiſdome that is thus precious? What is this that deſtruction and death have heard the fame of? Is it the wiſdome of nature? or is it Chriſt the wiſdome of God?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Where is the place of this? where doth God point man to find this wiſdome? He points him to the fear, <hi>Unto man he ſaid</hi> (he hath ſhewed thee, O man, what is good) <hi>Behold, the fear of the Lord, that is wiſdom, and to depart from evil is underſtanding.</hi> Go to the fear, there it is taught, that is the wiſdom: learn by the fear to depart from evil, that's the underſtanding. This is it which is ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, which nothing can equalize or value, here is the place of it, thus it is to be learned. Sin overſpreads all the land of darkneſſe, there is no fear of God before mens eyes there, there is no learning of the fear there, all the wiſdom that man can come by, cannot teach it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he that learneth to fear God, to depart from evil, muſt learn of Chriſt the wiſdom of God, and muſt deny all the varieties of the wiſdome of men, which undertakes to teach it, but cannot.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, What is that in every man which teachech the fear? which teacheth to depart from evil? Every man hath in him an eye that ſees the evil; what is that eye which the God of this world doth ſo ſtrive to blind, and doth ſo generally blind? Every man hath in him an enemy to evil, one that never conſented to it, but ſtill reproves it, and fights againſt it, even in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:96894:9"/>
ſecret: what is this? This is no leſs then a ray from Chriſt the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, out of the ſeat of the fear in every heart, to lead into the fear, where the Law of departing from eniquity is learned; and ſo this ray, being harkned unto, and followed in the fear, brings up into the love, into the life, into the light, into the wiſdome, into the power. Do not ſhut your eyes now, O ye wiſe ones, but open your hearts, and let in that which knocks there, which can and will ſave you, being let in, and which alone can ſave you, For it is not a notion of a Chriſt without (with multitudes of practiſes of ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal and mortification thereupon) which can ſave, but Chriſt heard knocking, and let into the heart. This will open the Scriptures aright; yea this is the true key, which will truly open words, things, and Spirits; but he that opens without this key, is a Thief and a Robber, and ſhall reſtore (in the day of Gods Judgment) all that he hath ſtollen; and woe to him, who when he is ſtripped of what he hath ſtollen, is found naked. The Scriptures were generally given forth to the people of God; part to the Jews, part to the Chriſtians. He that is born of the life, hath right unto them, and can read and underſtand them in the Spirit, which dwels in the life, But he that is not born of the Spirit, is but an intruder, and doth but ſteal other mens light, and other mens conditions and experiences into his carnal underſtanding, for which they were never intended, but only to be read and ſeen in that light which wrote them. And all theſe carnal apprehenſions of his (with all the faith, hope, love, knowledge; exerciſes, &amp;c. which he hath gained into his Spirit hereby, with all his prayers, tears and faſts, and other limitations) will become loſs to him, (for he muſt be ſtripped of them all, and become ſo much the more naked) when God recovers his Scriptures from mans dark Spirit (which hath torn them, and exceedingly prophaned them with his conceivings, gueſſings, and imaginings) and reſtores them again to his people. The Prophets, and Apoſtles who wrote Scripture, firſt had the life in them; and he who underſtands their words, muſt firſt have the life in him. He that underſtands words of life, muſt firſt have life in himſelfe. And the life (from which the word came) is the meaſurer of the words, and not the words of the life. And when the Scripture is interpreted by the life and Spirit which penned it, there is then no more jangling and contending about it; for all this is out of the life, from and in that Spirit, nature, and mind where the luſt, the enmity, the contention is, and not the unity, the love,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:96894:9"/>
the peace. But this is it which undoeth all, the dead ſpirit of man reads Scripture, and from that wiſdome which is in the death (not knowing the mind of the Spirit) gives meanings: and from believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and practiſing the things there ſpoken of (which death may do, as well as ſpeak of the fame) gathers an hope that all ſhall be well at laſt for Chriſts ſake, though it feel not the purification, the cleanſing, the circumciſion which cuts off the body of ſin and death here (for it is not to be cut off hereafter) and ſo gives an entrance into the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Kingdom, where the King of righteouſneſſe is ſeen, known, and worſhiped in ſpirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Fundamental Principle of the Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This then is the meſſage which we have heard of him, and declare unto you, That God is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.5.</p>
            <p>This was the meſſage which Chriſt gave his Apoſtles to make way into mens hearts by. This is the firſt thing that is proper for the mind to receive which lyes in the darkneſſe; namely, that there is no dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in God, nothing but light. Darkneſſe is excluded from him, and the mind that lies in darkneſſe cannot have union or fellowſhip with him: Therefore he that will be one with God, and partake of his life, muſt come out of the darkneſſe, which hath no place with God, into the light where God is, and in which he dwels.</p>
            <p>The work of the Son is to reveal the Father, and to draw to the Father. He reveals him as light (as the ſpring of light, as the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of light) and he draws to him as light. When he gives to his Apoſtles the ſtanding meſſage whereby they were to make him known to the world, and whereby men were to come into fellowſhip and acquaintance with him, this is it, <hi>That God is light, and in him is no darkneſs at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Chriſt Jeſus, the Son of God, he is the image of his ſubſtance, the exact image of this light, <hi>the light of the world,</hi> who is to light the world unto this ſubſtance. So that as God the Father is to be known as light, ſo Chriſt the Son alſo is to be known as light. He is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten of the Father of lights, the alone image wherein the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſubſtance is revealed and made known. And he that receives this image, receives the ſubſtance; and he that receives not this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage receives not the ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>Now there is a breath or ſpirit from this ſubſtance in this Image, which draws to this Image (thus the Father draws to the Son) and the Image again draws to the ſubſtance (thus the Son draws to the Father)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:96894:10"/>
And ſo hearkning to this breath, the mind and ſoul is led out of the darkneſſe into the Image of light (which is the Son) and by the Image into the ſubſtance: and heres the fellowſhip which the Goſpel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites to. Joyning to this breath, being transformed by this breath, living in this breath, walking in this holy inſpiration, there's an unity with the Father and the Son, who themſelves dwell in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> breath, from whom this breath comes, in whom this breath is, and in whom all are who are one with this breath.</p>
            <p>This breath purgeth out the dark breath, the dark air, the dark power, the miſtery of death and darkneſſe, and fils with the breath of light, with the breath of life, with the living power, with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pure miſtery.</p>
            <p>Now as the Father is light, and the Son light, ſo this breath, this ſpirit which proceeds from them both, is light alſo. And as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther who is light, can alone be revealed by the Son who is light: ſo the Son who is light, can alone be revealed by the ſpirit who is light.</p>
            <p>He then who hears this meſſage, that God is light, and feeleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf darkneſſe and in darkneſſe, and is willing to be drawn out of the darkneſſe, into fellowſhip with God who is light: This is requiſite for him to know, namely, how he may be drawn out, who it is that draws, and which are the drawings, that he may not reſiſt or neglect them (waiting for another thing) and ſo miſſe of the true and only paſſage unto life. Wherefore obſerve this heedfully.</p>
            <p>None can draw to the Father but the Son: none can draw to the Son but the Father: and both theſe alone draw by the ſpirit. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by his Spirit draws to the Son, and the Son by the ſame ſpirit draws to the Father: and they both draw by the ſpirit as he is light, as he is their light lighted to that end. For as the Father is light, and the Son light, ſo that Spirit which draws to them, muſt be light alſo. He is indeed the breath of light, eternally lighted, to draw to the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Image of light, and then to the eternal ſubſtance, which eternally dwels in that eternal Image.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But how may I know the Spirit and its operations, that I may follow him, and be led by him, both to the Son and to the Father, and ſo come into the everlaſting fellowſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The Spirit is to be known by thoſe motions &amp; operations which are proper to him, which flow alone from him, and from nothing elſe.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What are they?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Convincing of ſin, and reproving for ſin, which nothing can
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:96894:10"/>
truly diſcover and reprove but the light of the Spirit. Darkneſſe ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not make manifeſt darkneſſe, but whatſoever maketh manifeſt is light. All the diſcoveries of darkneſſe in the hidden world of the heart, are from Chriſt the Sun of Righteouſneſſe, by his Spirit, what name ſoever men may give it, who know not this Sun, nor its light, nor the true names of things in the light, but have named even the things of God in the dark, and according to the dark apprehenſions and conceptions of their own imaginary mind. But this I ſay to ſuch as are ſo ready to beat their brains and diſpute, leave contending about names, come to the thing, come to that which reproves thee in ſecret, follow the light that thus checks and draws; be diligent, be faithful, be obedient; thou ſhalt find this lead thee to that, which all thy knowledg out of this (even all that which thou calleſt Spiritual light) will never be able to lead thee.</p>
            <p>And when thou art joyned to this light, it will ſhew thee him whom thou haſt pierced (even ſo as never yet thou ſaweſt him) and open a freſh vain of blood and grief in thee, to bleed and mourn over him; and work that repentance in thee, which thou never waſt acquainted with before; and teach thee that faith, to which yet thou art a ſtranger; and teach thee that ſelf-denyal, which will reach to the very root of that nature which yet lives, even under that, and by means of that which thou calleſt ſpiritual light; and will lay ſuch an yoke on thy neck, as the unrighteou one is not able to bear, yea ſuch an one as the hypocrite which is able to hide it ſelf under confeſſions of ſin and forms of zeal, knowledg, devotion and worſhip) ſhall be daily tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented and waſted with. And then thou ſhalt know what it is to wait upon God in the way of his judgments, and find the powers of life and death ſtriving for thy ſoul, and daily floods and ſtormes encompaſſing and attending thee, under which thou wilt aſſuredly fall and periſh, unleſſe the everlaſting arm of Gods power be ſtretched out for thee, and be continually redeeming thee. And then thou wilt feel and ſee how ſin is pardoned, and how it is bound; how death brake in upon <hi>Adam,</hi> and how it daily breaks in upon mankind; and what that ſtandard is, which the ſpirit of the Lord lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up againſt the powers of darkneſſe. And then thou wilt come clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to perceive how that which thou haſt called religion formerly (which flowed not from this principle) hath been but the invention of thine own imaginary mind though thou fatheredſt it upon the Scriptures, as moſt men do moſt of their inventions about Doctrine and Worſhip)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:96894:11"/>
wherein thou haſt been in a dream of being changed, and yet remaineſt ſtill the ſame in nature, and haſt had a name that thou haſt lived, but art ſtill dead; a name of being ſanctified, but ſtill uncleane; a name of being juſtified, but ſtill condemned by the light in thine own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is one with him who is thy Judge, and who will judge according to it. And ſo, as that which is real taketh place in thee, ſo that which hath been but imaginary will paſſe away.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="catechism">
            <head>A ſhort Catechiſm, for the ſake of the ſimple-hearted.</head>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>VVHat is the eſtate and condition of all men by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as they are begotten of the ſeed of the evil doer, and come out of the loyns of the firſt</hi> Adam?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> A ſtate of ſin and darkneſſe, a ſtate of death and miſery, a ſtate of enmity againſt God, a ſtate accurſed from God, expoſed to his wrath and moſt righteous judgments, both here and hereafter.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What brought</hi> Adam <hi>to this eſtate? and what keeps the ſons of</hi> Adam <hi>in it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Feeding on the tree of knowledg, from which man is not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded to this day, though he is from the tree of life.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How came</hi> Adam <hi>at firſt, and how come men ſtill to feed on the tree of knowledg?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> From a luſtful appetite and deſire after the forbidden wiſdom, ſown in their hearts by the envious enemy of their ſouls, who is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually twining about this tree, and tempting men and women to eat of it, perſwading them that the fruit thereof is good for food: and indeed it is very deſirable to their eye, and promiſeth fair to make them everlaſtingly wiſe, but ſtill faileth.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the forbidden fruit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is knowledg without life, knowledg in the earthly part, knowledg acquired from below, not given from above. This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth to make men as God, and to give them the ability of diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and diſtinguiſhing between good and evil, which is Gods pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar property. Eating of this fruit undid <hi>Adam,</hi> undid the Gentiles, undid the Jews, undid the Chriſtians, they all feeding on the tree of knowledg, and departing from the life in their ſeveral diſpenſations.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How doth this fruit undo man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The wiſdom and knowledg (which they thus gather and feed upon) perverts them, makes them wiſe in the wrong part, exalts
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:96894:11"/>
them againſt the life, duls the true appetite, and increaſes the wrong appetite, in ſo much as that there is not ſo much as a deſire in them after God in truth, but only to get knowledg and wiſdom from what they can comprehend. By this means whatſoever was afterwards or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to life, became death to man. Thus the Gentiles liked not to retain God in their knowledg, but fell by their diſpenſation, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking God to caſt them off, and give them up to the vanity of their imaginations. And thus the Jews (whom God then choſe) fell like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by their diſpenſation, God for this cauſe giving them up to their own hearts luſts, and rejecting them from being a people. And the Gentiles (whom God ingrafted into the true Olive, in the Jews ſtead) they alſo after the ſame manner fell by their diſpenſation. Thus each of theſe fell by gathering wiſdom from the letter, but miſſing of the life in every of theſe diſpenſations.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is the food which man ſhould feed on?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The tree of life, the word which liveth and abideth for ever, which is in the midſt of the garden of God, which word was made fleſh for mans weakneſſe ſake, on which fleſh the living ſoul feeds, and whoſe blood the living ſpirit drinks, and ſo is nouriſhed up to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But had</hi> Adam <hi>this food to feed on? and was this to be the food of the Gentiles, Jews and Chriſtians in their ſeveral diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> God breathed into man the breath of life, and man became a living ſoul: and nothing leſſe then life it ſelf could ſatisfie his ſoul at firſt, nor can to this day. Every word of God that cometh freſh out of his mouth, is mans food and life. And God ſpeaketh often to man, ſhewing him what is good, but he cannot reliſh or feed on this, but deſireth ſomewhat elſe, through the error and alienation of his mind. And what God ſpeaketh now to man (if that be mans life) <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> had much more of it before his fall. And for the Jews, <hi>Moſes</hi> tells them the word was nigh them, in their heart, and in their mouth: and <hi>Paul</hi> alſo tels the Chriſtians ſo. So that the word is not far from any man, but mens ears are generally ſtopped againſt it, by the ſubtilty of the ſerpent, which at firſt deceived them.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But did not the Jews ſeek for eternal life, in reading and ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Scriptures under their diſpenſation? and do not the Chriſtians now ſeek for life, and to feed on life?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea they did, and do in their own way, but they refuſe it in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:96894:12"/>
Gods way. Thus <hi>Adam</hi> after he had eat of the tree of knowledg, would have fed on the tree of life alſo, but he was ſhut out then, and ſo are Chriſtians now. And if ever they will feed on the tree of life, they muſt looſe their knowledge, they muſt be made blind, and be led to it by a way that they know not.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>This is too miſterious for me, give me the plain literal knowledg of the Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Is not the ſubſtance a myſtery? is not the life there? The letter of any diſpenſation killeth: it is the ſpirit alone that giveth life. A man may read the letter of the Scripture diligently and gather a large knowledg therefrom, and feed greedily thereon, but it is only the dead ſpirit which ſo feeds, but the ſoul underneath is lean, barren, hungry and unſatisfied, which when it awakes, it will feel.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But may not the dead ſpirit ar well imagine myſteries in every thing, and feed thereon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea it may, and the error here is greater then the former: but in waiting in the humilty and fear, to have the true eye opened, and the true myſtery revealed to the humble and honeſt heart, and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of that in the demonſtration of the ſpirit, out of the wiſdom of the fleſh, here is no error, but the true knowledge, which ſprings from life, and brings life.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may I come at this myſtery?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is but one key can open it, but one hand can turn that key, and but one veſſel, but one heart, but one ſpirit, which can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the knowledge.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How may I come by that heart?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> As thou being touched with the enemy didſt let him in, and didſt not thruſt him by with the power of that life which was ſtronger th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n he, and nearer to thee. Even ſo now, when thou art touched and drawn by thy friend, (who is nigh) and thereby findeſt the beginning of vertue entering into thee, give up in and by that life and vertue, and wait for more; and ſtill as thou feeleſt that following, calling, and growing upon thee; follow on in it, and it will lead thee in a wonderful way out of the land of death and darkneſſe, where thy ſoul hath been a captive, into the land of life and perfect liberty.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But can I do any thing toward my own ſalvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Of thy ſelf thou canſt not, but in the power of him that work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth both to will and to do, thou mayſt do a little at firſt: and as that power grows in thee, thou wilt be able to will more, and to do more,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:96894:12"/>
even until nothing become too hard for thee. And when thou haſt conquered all, ſuffered all, performed all, thou ſhalt ſee, and be able underſtandingly to ſay, Thou haſt done nothing, but the eternal vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, life and power hath wrought all in thee.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>I perceive, by what is ſaid, that there is a Saviour, one which hath virtue, life and power in him to ſave, but how may I meet with him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea, he that made man pittieth him, and is not willing that he ſhould periſh in the pit into which he fell, but hath appointed one to draw him out, and ſave him.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Who is this Saviour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> He is the Tree of Life I have ſpoken of all this while, whoſe leaves have virtue in them to heal the Nations. He is the plant of righteouſneſſe, the plant of Gods right hand (haſt thou ever known ſuch a plant in thee, planted there by the right hand of God?) He is the Reſurrection and the Life, which raiſeth the dead ſoul, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it to live. He is the ſpiritual Manna, whereupon the quickned ſoul feeds. Yea, his fleſh is meat indeed, and his blood is drink indeed, which he that is raiſed up in the life feeds on, and findeth the living vertue in them which ſatisfieth and nouriſheth up his immortal ſoul.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But hath not this Saviour a name? What is his name?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It were better for thee to learn his name by feeling his vertue and power in thy heart, then by rote. Yet (if thou canſt receive it) this is his name, <hi>The light, the light of the World,</hi> (a light to enlighten the Gentiles, that he may convert and make them Gods <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and become their glory.) And according to his Office, he hath enlightned every man that cometh into the world, though men neither know the light that cometh from him, nor him from whom the light comes; and ſo notwithſtanding the light is ſo near them, remain ſtrangers to it, and unſaved by it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why doſt thou call him the light? are there not other names every whit as proper, whereby he may as well be known?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Do not thus let up the wiſe and ſtumbling part in thee, but mind the thing, which firſt puts forth its virtue as light, and ſo is thus firſt to be known, owned, and received. Yet more particularly, if thou haſt wherewith, conſider this reaſon: We call him light, becauſe the father of lights hath peculiarly choſen this name for him, to make him known to his people in this age by, and hath thus made him manifeſt to us. And by thus receiving him, under this name,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:96894:13"/>
we come to know his other names. He is the life, the righteouſneſſe, the power, the wiſdom, the peace, &amp;c. but he is all theſe in the light, and in the light we learn and receive them all: and they are none of them to be known in ſpirit, but in and by the light.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How are the other names of Chriſt known in and by the light?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Letting in the light (which convinceth of, and warreth againſt ſin) the life ſtirs and is felt, and the life leads to the word which was in the beginning, and gives the feeling of that alſo. And in the word, the righteouſneſſe, the peace, the wiſdom, the power, the love is felt; and he is made all theſe to thoſe who are led into, and kept in the light. And when the powers of darkneſſe appear with mighty dread, and there is no ſtrength to withſtand them, this lifts up a ſtandard againſt them, and calms all the tempeſts, and cures all the wounds and diſeaſes of the ſoul, anointing it with the everlaſting oil, ſo that now I can ſenſibly, and with clear underſtanding call it my Saviour, the Captain of my ſalvation, my Chriſt or anointed, my Husband, my King, my Lord, my God.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Where doth this light ſhine?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the darkneſſe at firſt: but when it hath vanquiſhed, expelled and diſperſed the darkneſſe, it ſhines out of it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is that darkneſs wherein the light ſhines?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Man: mans heart, mans conſcience, mans ſpirit. This is the world, which Chriſt the Sun of righteouſneſſe is the light of, in every part whereof he cauſeth the rayes or beams of his light to ſhine at his pleaſure, though in no part the darkneſſe can comprehend the leaſt ſhining of his light?</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How then can it ever be converted thereby?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The darkneſſe is not to be converted. Every man in this ſtate is reprobated, and the wrath abideth on him. So that the darkneſſe is rejected, and man in the darkneſſe; but man touched by the light, made ſenſible of it, and following it in the life and power which it begets, is drawn out of the horrible pit, and ſaved.</p>
            <p>Q <hi>How may I do to find the light in the midſt of the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kneſs of my heart, which is ſo great, and this ſeed ſo ſmall?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By its diſcovering and warring againſt the darkneſſe. There is ſomewhat which diſcovereth both the open and ſecret iniquity of the corrupt heart, following it under all its coverings of zeal, holineſſe, and all manner of voluntary humility, and ſelf righteouſneſſe (with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:96894:13"/>
which the true light <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ver had unity) and ſometimes may cauſe ſecret miſgivings that all is not well, but there may be a flaw found in this covering, and in the end it may prove too narrow for the ſoul. This which thus warreth againſt the darkneſſe, to bring people off from all falſe foundations, to the true and living foundation, this is the light, and thus thou maiſt find it, at ſome time or other at work in thy heart, if thou mind it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Having found the light, how may I come to feel the ſaving ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and power of it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By believing in it. For the vertue and power ſprings up in the heart that believes in it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How can I believe in it, am not I dead?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There is a creating, a quickning power in the light, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets a little life, and that can anſwer the voice of the living power.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Yea, If I could finde any ſuch thing begotten in me, then I might be drawn to aſſent that that (though never ſo ſmall) might believe, but ſurely my dead heart never can.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Haſt thou never found a true honeſt breathing towards God? haſt thou never found ſin, not an imaginary, but a real burthen? This was from life; there was ſomewhat begotten of God in thee, which felt this: It was not fleſh &amp; blood in thee, but ſomwhat from above. And if this had known the ſpring of its life, and not been deceived from it by the ſubtilty, it would have fed upon, and have grown up in the vertue and power of the ſpring, from whence its life came.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Why then, by this, all men have power to believe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> In the light which ſhines in all, and viſits all, there is the power: and this power ſtrives with the creature to work it ſelf into the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and where there hath been the leaſt breathing after life, there hath been a taſte of the power: for this came from it. But the great deceiver of ſouls, lifts up mens mind in the imagination, to look for ſome great appearance of power, and ſo they ſlight and overlook the day of ſmall things, and neglect receiving the beginnings of that, which in the iſſue would be the thing they look for. Waiting in that which is low and little in the heart, the power enters, the ſeed grows, the Kingdom is felt, and daily more and more revealed in the power. And this is the true way and door to the thing, take heed of climbing over it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What is it to believe in the light?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> To receive its teſtimony either concerning good or evil: and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:96894:14"/>
ſo either to turn towards or from, in the will and power which the light begets in the heart.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How will this ſave me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By this means, that in thee which deſtroys thee (and ſeparates thee from the living God) is daily wrought out, and the heart daily changed into the Image of him who is light, and brought into unity and fellowſhip with the light, poſſeſſing of it, and being poſſeſſed by it, and this is Salvation.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>We thought ſalvation had been a thing to be beſtowed hereafter, after the death of the body: but if it be thus, then ſalvation is wrought out here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> So it is, even in all that are ſaved: for there is no working of it out hereafter, but here it is wrought out with fear and trembling, and the believer (who is truly in unity with the life) daily changed from glory to glory, as by the Spirit of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But ſhew more particularly, how Faith or believing in the light worketh out the Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Firſt, it cauſeth a fear and trembling to ſeize upon the ſinner. The Lord God Almighty, by the riſing of his light in the heart, cauſeth the powers of darkneſſe to ſhake, the earth to tremble, the hills and mountains to melt, and the goodly fruit-Trees to caſt their fruit. And then the plant of the Lord ſprings up out of the dry and barren ground, which by the dews and ſhowers from above, thrives, grows, and ſpreads till it fills Gods earth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In this fear and trembling, the work of true repentantance and converſion is begun and carried on. There is a turning of the Soul from the darkneſſe to the light; from the dark power to the power of light; from the ſpirit of deceit, to the Spirit of truth, from all falſe appearances and imaginations about holineſs, to that which the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal light manifeſteth to be truly ſo. And now is a time of mourning, of deep mourning, while the ſepartion is working, while the enemies ſtrength is not broken and ſubdued, and while the heart is now and then feeling it ſelf, ſtill hankering after its old lovers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the belief of the light, and in the fear placed in the heart, there ſprings up an hope, a living hope in the living principle, which hath manifeſted it ſelf and begun to work. For the Soul truly turning to the light, the everlaſting Arm, the living power is felt: and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor being felt, it ſtaies the ſoul in all the toſſings, troubles, ſtorms, and tempeſts it meets with afterwards, which are many, yea very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:96894:14"/>4. Faith, through the hope works righteouſneſſe, and teaches the true wiſdom (and now the benefit of all the former trouble, anguiſh and miſery begins to be felt, and the work goes on ſweetly.) All un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs is in the darkneſſe, in the unbelief, in the falſe hope; faith in the light works out the unrighteouſneſſe, and works in the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of God in Chriſt. And it makes truly wiſe, wiſe in the living power, even wiſe againſt the evil and to the good, which no man can learn elſewhere.</p>
            <p n="5">5. In the righteouſneſſe, and in the true wiſdome which is received in the light, there ſprings up a love, and an unity and fellowſhip with God the Father of lights, and with all who are children of the light. Being begotten by Chriſt the light, into the nature of the light, and brought forth in the Image, there is an unity ſoon felt with God the Father, and with thoſe who are born of the ſame womb, and partake of the ſame nature. And here is a willingneſſe and power felt in this love, to lay down the life, even for the leaſt truth of Chriſts, or for the brethren.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Belief in the light works patience, meekneſſe, gentleneſſe, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe and long ſuffering. It will bear any thing for God, any thing for mens ſouls ſake. It will wait quietly and ſtilly for the carrying on of the work of God in its own ſoul, and for the manifeſtation of Gods love and mercy to others. It will bear the contradiction and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of ſinners, ſeeking their good, even while they are plotting, contriving and hatching miſchief, laying many ſubtil ſnares, and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereby to entrap the innocent.</p>
            <p n="7">7. It brings peace, joy, and glory. Faith in the light breaks down the wall of darkneſſe, the wall of Partition, that which ſeparates from the peace, that which cauſeth the anguiſh and trouble upon the ſoul, and ſo brings into peace. Chriſt is the skilful Phyſitian, he cures the diſeaſe by removing the cauſe. The unskilful Phyſitians they heale deceitfully, crying peace, peace, while there is no peace, while that which breaks the peace is ſtanding; but Chriſt doth not ſo, but ſlaies the enmity in the heart by the blood of his croſſe, ſo making peace. And this is true peace certain peace.</p>
            <p>Now finding the clods of earth removed, the enemy, the diſturber, the peace-breaker trodden down, the ſin taken away, the life &amp; power preſent, the ſoul brought into the peace, here's joy, unſpeakable joy, joy which the world cannot ſee or touch, nor the powers of darkneſſe come neer to interrupt. Here's now no more crying out, <hi>O wretched
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:96894:15"/>
man: and who ſhall deliver,</hi> &amp;c. but a rejoycing in him who hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven victory, and made the ſoul a conqueror, yea more then a conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror. Wait to feel that, thou who art now groaning, and oppreſſed by the mercileſſe powers of darkneſſe. And this joy is full of glory, which glory increaſeth daily more and more, by the daily ſight and feeling of the living vertue and power in Chriſt the light, whereby the ſoul is continually transformed (and changed more and more) out of the corruptible, into the incorruptible; out of the uncircumciſion, the ſhame, the reproach, into the circumciſion, the life, the glory.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Doth the light do all this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea, in them that turn towards it, give up to it, and abide in it. In them it cleanſeth out the thickneſſe, and darkneſſe, and daily trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth them into the image, purity and perfection of the light. And this nothing can do but the light alone.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What makes men generally ſo averſe from the light?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Their unity with the darkneſſe, which the light is an enemy to, diſcovering and diſturbing it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But wiſe men, knowing men (men who are looked upon as having moſt light) they alſo are enemies to this light, and ſpeak hardly of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Was it not alwayes ſo? Did any of the Rulers or wiſe Scribes and Teachers of the Law believe in him formerly? and is it any won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der if ſuch believe not in him now?</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>What may be the reaſon, why the wiſe men formerly have not, and now cannot believe in the light?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> There are two great reaſons for it:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe they cannot comprehend it. They can comprehend the knowledg which they can gather out of the book of Nature, or out of the books of the Law and Prophets, or out of the books of the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts and Apoſtles, but they cannot comprehend the light which all theſe teſtifie of (ſo that ſuch a kind of knowledg they can receive, but the light they cannot) for it is not to be comprehended, but gathereth into it ſelf, and comprehendeth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe it is an utter enemy to them. It will not wink at the clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of their evils, nor ſpeak peace to them therein. Their own gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red knowledg may ſpeak peace to them, but this will not. Thus the Jews could ſpeak peace to themſelves, from their Temple, Ordinances and Sactifices, though they walked in the ſtubborneſs and uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their hearts, reſiſting the checks and motions of the holy ſpirit there: &amp; thus the Chriſtians can ſpeak peace to themſelvs from a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:96894:15"/>
and hope through Chriſts dying at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (though they know not him in them, and are at a diſtance, and not one with that in their hearts which is of Chriſt, and in his power and authority checks and reproves for ſin) but the light will not ſpeak peace ſo, but only where the vertue of the living blood is felt, cleanſing away the ſin.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But there are many profeſſors, ſtrict profeſſors (who, without doubt have once taſted of the living virtue) what makes them ſuch enemies to the light? for there are none ſpeaks more againſt it then they.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. Becauſe they are fallen from what they once had, for if they were in that living principle, which once gave them a true taſte of life through the Scriptures, they could not but know &amp; own the light, which was the thing which gave them the taſte, and would have preſerved their reliſh, had they known how to turn to it, and abide in it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The light is a witneſſe againſt all their knowledg and religious practiſes &amp; imitations from the Scripture, which they hold &amp; practiſe out of the light, in the unrighteouſneſſe, even in that part which is not to know or be the worſhipper. And can ye blame them, that when the light is ſo great an enemy to them, that they alſo turn head againſt it? How is it poſſible, that having ſlain and murdered the juſt one in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they ſhould acknowledg and give him his due honour in others?</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But have the ſtrict profeſſors, who pretend great things in honour of Chriſt, murthered him in themſelves?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea verily, as really as the Scribes, Phariſees and people of the Jews put him to death at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> for what they do to the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of his light in their hearts, they do it unto him: Yea, our Lord Chriſt at this very day, is as really crucified in their ſpiritual <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> and <hi>Sodom,</hi> as he was without the gates of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and his righteous blood cries as loud againſt the profeſſors of this age, as ever it did againſt the Jews: and they are hardned againſt him by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited knowledg, which by their imaginations they have gathered from the Scriptures, juſt as the Jews were, but the eye in them can no more ſee it, then the eye in the Jews could.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Surely if they knew the light to be the only living way, they would not be ſuch enemies to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Yea I believe concerning them (as was ſaid concerning the Jews) that if they knew it, they would not crucifie the Lord of glory: for I bear many of them record, that they have a great zeal, though not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to knowledg. But at preſent very ſad is their ſtate; for the God of the world hath blinded that eye in them, which alone can ſee
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:96894:16"/>
the truth; and with that eye, wherewith they now ſtrive to ſee, they ſhall never ſee with comfort. Yea, ſo exceeding groſs and thick are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them become, and their hearts ſo fat, that in ſtead of feeling the want of the ſpirit of God in themſelves, and mourning after it, they can mock at the appearances of it in others, and ſpeak contemptibly of a light within, where Chriſt ſaith the light is: For, ſaith Chriſt, Take heed that the light which is in thee be not darkneſſe, for if, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But will not they reply, that they do not oppoſe (much leſs mock at) the light of the ſpirit, but only that which ye ignorantly call the light of the ſpirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> If we have found it to be the light of the ſpirit, and to work that in us and for us, which no other light ever could, do not blame us for giving in our teſtimony that it is that light. And take heed how ye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach us with ignorance, ſeeing many of us have paſſed through all that which ye call knowledg: but our light is a new and ſtrange thing to you, and ye are not yet able to judge it.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But may not men obtain eternal life by reading the Scriptures, without knowing or owning this principle of the light?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The true end of mens reading the Scriptures, is to turn them to the light. The Scriptures contain meſſages concerning God, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chriſt, concerning the Spirit, the end whereof is to turn men to the power and life, which can do the thing for them: which God, which Chriſt, which Spirit fill all things, and are within in the heart, as well as without. The word is nigh thee, in thy heart, and in thy mouth, ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> to the Jews, ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to the Chriſtians. And to what end do they tell them it is there? but that there they ſhould wait upon it, to hear its voice, and to obey it. Now mark, though men could practiſe and perform all things mentioned in the Scriptures, yet not being turned to this, they are not in the way of ſalvation: for the way of ſalvation is not a particular path or courſe of Ordinances and duties preſcribed in the Scriptures, but it is a new way, a living way, a way that the wiſeſt profeſſors, out of it never knew (I will lead them in paths they have not known.) So that while men know not, nor are not turned to the light and power whereof the Scriptures teſtifie, all their reading of the Scriptures, praying and practiſing Ordinances and duties there men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, are but in vain, and in the end will prove but a falſe cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not the covering of the ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But how did men do formerly? for this is but a late notion about the light; have none ever been ſaved that have not embraced this notion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:96894:16"/>
               <hi>A.</hi> I ſpeak not of embracing a notion, but of turning to the thing it ſelf, whithout which none ever was, or can be ſaved: for it is that alone can ſave, and it ſaves only them that are turned to it. Now if any man ſo read the Scriptures, as thereby to learn to turn to this, he may feel that which will work ſalvation in him, though he know not its name. For as darkneſſe, being turned to, works death in a miſtery, though its name be not known, but it may appear and be taken for light; ſo light being tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ned to, works life in a miſtery, although he in whom it works, ſhould not be able to call it by its name.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>Then by this, a man may be ſaved, though he ſhould not know the litteral name Jeſus, or the litteral name Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> The names are but the ſignification of the things ſpoken of, for it is the life, the power (the being transformed by that) that ſaves, not the knowledg of a name. And Chriſtians mightily deceive themſelves herein, for they think to be ſaved by believing a relation concerning Chriſt, as he appeared in a fleſhly body, and ſuffered death at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> Whereas Chriſt is the ſame yeſterday, to day, and for ever: and the ſaving knowledg reveals him, not only as he was then, but as he was the day before, and as he will be for ever. And this knowledg is alſo revealed in the Scripture, but they are ſo drowned in the Letter, wherewith the carnal part is ſo filled, that the ſpiritual eye cannot open in them to ſee: and ſo that which was ordained for life, becomes death to them, and they periſh, they periſh juſt as the Jews did: for their eyes are with held by a wiſdom which they have grown up in from the Letter, from the beholding the miſtery of life in the ſpirit, which alone can work out, and ſave from the miſtery of death.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>But did not God formerly work life in men by their reading of the Scriptures, and by the preaching of ſuch godly Miniſters, as are now deſpiſed, and counted Antichriſtian?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> When men read the Scriptures formerly in the times of thick darkneſſe, and when ſome of thoſe (who were not made Miniſters ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of the Goſpel) preached in the ſimplicity of their hearts, according to the beſt light of their feeling and experience, the Lord pitied the ſimplicity of their hearts, and ſecretly refreſhed this principle in them by ſuch reading, and by ſuch preaching. But now this principle is made manifeſt, their reading and ſetting up a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the Scriptures without this (which was the thing even then from whence they had their life) yea in oppoſition to this, this increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth their death and bondage, and ſhuts them out of life.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:96894:17"/>Q. <hi>Well I will keep to the Scriptures, and wait for light there, let who will follow this new light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Wilt thou keep to the Scriptures in oppoſition to that light, which alone can give thee the knowledg of the Scriptures? what kind of knowledg wilt thou gather from the Scriptures? Not a knowledge which will humble thee, and cleanſe thy heart; but a knowledg which will puff thee up, and fit thee for the ſlaughter. While thou art from the light, thou canſt not know the Scriptures, nor the power of God, but art exalting thine own imaginations, conceivings, and reaſonings about the ſenſe of Scriptures. And this thou wilt one day know with ſorrow, when God calls thee to an account for thy boldneſſe, in putting ſenſes and meanings upon his words without his light.</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>I am almoſt ſtartled?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Many have fallen, and more muſt fall: for the ſharp Axe of the Lord is preparrd to cut down every profeſſor, with all his profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and religious practiſes &amp; imitations from Scripture, which ſtand not in the pure life. Happy art thou, if thou now fall by that hand, which now ſtrikes at many in great loving kindneſſe and mercy, that he might raiſe them up again, and fix them firm on the true foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But miſerable are thoſe, whoſe eyes are withheld, till the day of their viſitation be overſlipt, and ſo they continue keeping their corrupt ſtanding, and confidence in their fleſhly knowledg of Scriptures, for they alſo muſt fall, but their fall will be otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>Mind therefore this my ſingle hearted advice.</p>
            <p>Let thy Religion be to feel the pure principle of life in the pure veſſel of life, for the eye muſt be pure that ſees the life, and the heart that receives it. And faith is a pure myſtery, and it is only held in a pure conſcience. Know that in thee that purifies thee, and then thou knoweſt Chriſt, and the Father and the Spirit: and as that lives and grows up in thee, ſo ſhalt thou know their dwelling place, and partake of their life and fulneſſe.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:96894:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
